A Guide to the G. T. Beauregard Papers, 1862-1863
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
G. T. Beauregard Papers, 1862-1863
The Library of Virginia
21324
20 leaves
G. T. Beauregard
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying by the Fort Orange Stamp Club, Albany, New York, through Edgar Stanley, 1938.
Alternative Form Available
Originals available, except for invoice of ordnance and ordnance stores turned over by Captain J. L. White (accession 22054).
Biographical Information
Pierre Gustave Toutant Beauregard was born 28 May 1818 in Saint Bernard Parish, Louisiana. Graduating second in the class of 1838 from West Point, he served as an engineer officer on the staff of General Winfield Scott during the Mexican war and earned two brevets. In January 1861, Beauregard was appointed superintendent of the United States Military Academy, but was relieved shortly thereater. Resigning his commission from the United States army in February 1861, he accepted a commission as a brigadier-general in the Confederate army 1 March. Commanding the troops in Charleston, South Carolina, Beauregard directed the siege of Fort Sumter culminating in its surrender 13 April 1861, starting the Civil War. Beauregard was second in command during the 1st battle of Bull Run (Manassas) and received a commission as a full general dating from 21 July 1861. Second in command to Albert Sidney Johnston (1803-1862)in the West, Beauregard took command of Confederate forces at Shiloh, Tennessee, when Johnston was killed, 6-7 April 1862, and retreated to Corinth, Mississippi, which was later abandoned due to a large Union advance. Ill, Beauregard took leave and was replaced in command by Braxton Bragg (1817-1876). He later commanded the defense of the South Carolina and Georgia coasts, most notably defending Charleston from assaults in 1863 and 1864. In May 1864, Beauregard commanded troops in Virginia, and prevented Union troops from capturing Petersburg, Virginia. Second in command to Joseph E. Johnston (1807-1891) when the war ended, Beauregard returned to New Orleans, Louisiana. After the Civil War, he served as the president of two railroads and supervised the drawings of the Louisiana lottery. Beauregard died 20 February 1893 and was buried in New Orleans.
Scope and Content
File copies of letters and telegrams, 1862-1863, of General G. T. Beauregard (1818-1893) of Louisiana discussing the strategic importance of Corinth, Mississippi; his replacement in command of the western army by General Braxton Bragg (1817-1876); the military situation in the western Confederacy; Beauregard's health; Beauregard's comments on the defense of Mobile, Alabama, and Charleston, South Carolina; and his review on the possibility of retaking New Orleans, Louisiana, from the Union army; defects of Confederate iron clads. Also includes an invoice of ordnance and orndance stores.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Location of Originals
Originals (accession 22054) available at The Library of Virginia, except for invoice of ordnance and ordnance stores turned over by Captain J. L. White.
Contents List
- Letter, 19 May 1862, from Beauregard to Samuel Cooper, adjutant and inspector general, C.S.A. commenting on the strategic importance of Corinth, Mississippi.
- Telegram, 14 June 1862, from Beauregard to Cooper, requesting that General Braxton Bragg temporarily replace Beauregard.
- Letter, 23 June 1862, from Secretary of War George Wythe Randolph to Beauregard containing copies of telegrams from Randolph and President Jefferson Davis to Bragg permanently assigning Bragg to Beauregard's command.
- Memorandum, 24 June 1862, drawn up by Colonel William Preston Johnston, aide-de-camp to Davis, concerning a conversation between Johnston and Beauregard about conditions in the West.
- Letter, 25 June 1862, from Beauregard to Cooper informing Cooper that he is taking leave to regain his health.
- Letter, 18 July 1862, from Beauregard to Brigadier-General John Horace Forney, offering suggestions on defending Mobile, Alabama.
- Letter, 25 July 1862, from Beauregard to Major-General Gustavus W. Smith commenting on improvements of the defenses of Charleston, South Carolina.
- Letter, 2 August 1862, from Beauregard to Colonel John M. Huger reviewing the possibility of retaking New Orleans from Union forces.
- Letter, 2 September 1862, from R. L. Brodie, surgeon in Mobile, Alabama, to Charles J. Villere, Louisiana congressman, reporting on Beauregard's health.
- "Remarks relative to Iron Clad Gun Boats," 14 November 1863, in which Beauregard cites six defects of Confederate gunboats and suggests the type of vessels which should be used.
- Invoice of ordnance and ordnance stores turned over by Captain J. L. White.